Ely Samuel Parker Papers 1794-1946 Mss.497.3.P223
American Philosophical Society
- Series I. Correspondence, 1794-1946; 1.5 linear feet
  - Seneca and Wyandot tradition, 1848 [May?]; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 2)
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1848 June 14; Parker, Nicholson H. (Box 2)
    A letter from Batavia, informing his brother that the Courts fined Ichabod Waldren $15.00, that other complaints have been made against the intruders, and that Blacksmith has received a letter from Brown concerning losses of money by Striker.
  - DS, 1848 [June?]; "Tonawanda Reservation" (Box 2)
    Statement that William Parker, as part owner of the saw mill, is entitled "to $47.90 of the $100.00 payment."
  - ALS to Nicholson H. Parker, 1848 Aug. 16; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 2)
    Letter from Ellicottville stating Ely will need money by September to attend the State fair in Buffalo, and that Mr. Angel has been replaced by Robert H. Shankland as Indian agent.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1848 Sept. 16; Flagler, Henry M. (Box 2)
    A letter from a friend, with comments on politics and news of family and friends.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1848 Sept. 16; Morgan, Lewis Henry, 1818-1881 (Box 2)
    Morgan cannot attend council on September 30 and requests Ely to send him a full report, including speeches of the orators, description of the ceremony of raising up sachems, the white dog sacrifice, etc., to be used in connection with a book Morgan plans to publish on the League of the Iroquois.
  - ALS to Tonawanda Chiefs, 1848 Sept. 28; Shankland, R. H. (Box 2)
    The new Indian Agent reports that the annuity money has been received and will be paid Oct. 18 to the heads of families, in accordance with a new method.
  - "Council of the Six Nations", 1848 Oct. 4-5; [Wright, Asher?] (Box 2)
    A notebook containing a report of speeches, etc., in pencil. Also typescript of same, with photostat of first and last pages of original.
  - AMs, 1848 [Oct.?] 4-7; [Parker, Ely S.] (Box 2)
    Mutilated manuscript describing "a Grand Council of the Six Nations of New York, held at Tonawanda for the purpose of hearing again their religious code, from Jimmy Johnson, the Grand High Priest of the Iroquois Confederacy."
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1848 Oct. 23; Cone, Spencer H. (Box 2)
    Letter with news of the early victims of what may be a small pox epidemic.
  - Pr. speech, 1848 Oct. 29; Wilson, Peter (Box 2)
    Printed "Speech of Wa-o-wa-wa-na-onk [Peter Wilson], addressed to the Committee of Baltimore Yearly Meeting of Friends on Indian Concerns, 10 mo. 29, 1848."
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1848 Oct. 30; Morgan, Lewis Henry, 1818-1881 (Box 2)
    A letter requesting Seneca names for items in Morgan's Indian collection which, according to a plan of the Regents of the University, is to form a department of the State Geological Collection.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1848 Nov. 26; Cone, Spencer H. (Box 2)
    Spencer advises his brother that the Supreme Court has decided a case in the Indians' favor. A council is to be held to decide on the manner in which annuities are to be paid. Smallpox is confined to Poodry's family and is not spreading.
  - AMss, 1848 [Nov. 30]; Parker, Nicholson H. (Box 2)
    A collection of essays with the following titles: The Young Twig; On Mohammed; The Wreath of Love; Time (dated Nov. 30, 1848); An Amateur President; Troubles of Life; Alphabetical Allitteration; Stray Thoughts; etc.
  - ALS to [Ely S. Parker], 1848 Dec. 10; Parker, William H. (Box 2)
    The father discusses Ely's letter of Nov. 20 "the contents of which is at so much variance to yours of the 20th ult." Contrary to Ely's later advice some of the Tonawandas are opposed to accepting the new method of annuity payments and are inclined to link it with the Ogden Co.'s efforts to appraise improvements. Wm. Parker accuses Dr. Wilson at Cattaraugus of being "the main and prime mover of our present difficulties."
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1848 Dec. 13; Flagler, Henry M. (Box 2)
    Letter from a friend, extolling the pleasures and amusements available in Bellevue, Ohio.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1848 Dec. 14; Morgan, Lewis Henry, 1818-1881 (Box 2)
    Letter advising Parker of the disappointing results of calls on newspaper editors, which Morgan has made as requested in an attempt to secure work for Ely as a correspondent should he decide to go West. As an inducement to "abandon his Western notions," Morgan tells Ely of contacts he has made to secure employment for him with the State's Genessee Valley Canal project. Asks him again for a description by Johnson of the white dog sacrifice and for a few more Indian words.
  - ALS to Lewis Henry Morgan, 1848 Dec. 23; Pomeroy, Henry. (Box 2)
    Letter advising there will be no vacancy for Parker until the Spring.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1848 Dec. 29; Morgan, Lewis Henry, 1818-1881 (Box 2)
    Letter enclosing Pomeroy's reply of Dec. 23.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1849 Jan. 16; Warren, R. B. (Box 3)
    Warren, who has been recently married, reports that "Wadsworth, surveyors and appraisers" have been driven off by the Indians and that Sheriff Sprague and the Secretary of War refused to aid the efforts of these Ogden agents to appraise the Tonawandas' improvements.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1849 Feb. 21; Warren, R. B. (Box 3)
    Letter commenting on Parker's new position and giving news of friends. Warren also reports that "Wadsworth and Co." are attempting to appraise improvements through information obtained from White informers. He encloses an article from the Democrat, to which he urges Parker to reply giving the Indians' side of the Ogden matter.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1849 Mar. 7; Flagler, Henry M. (Box 3)
    An acknowledgement of Parker's letter of Feb. 16. Warren is glad to know Ely likes his new work. He states "California is all the rage here." The number of Sons of Temperance is compared to the larger membership among the Odd Fellows and Masons in Bellevue.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1849 Mar. 11; Schoolcraft, Henry Rowe, 1793-1864 (Box 3)
    Brief note advising Parker he has written Mr. Brown, informing him that Wadsworth is in Washington, urging the appointment of a new appraiser to replace Mr. Love, who is expected to resign.
  - LS to William L. Marcy, 1849 [Mar. 12?]; Tonawanda Chiefs (Box 3)
    Incomplete letter to the Secretary of War, objecting to the application of the Ogden Co. for a new appraiser to replace Thomas C. Love.
  - TDS Cy, 1849 Mar. 13; Tonawanda Chiefs (Box 3)
    Typed copy of power-of-attorney, signed by 18 chiefs, authorizing Nicholson H. Parker to "speak, act and decide," on their behalf in dealing with officers of the state and federal governments.
  - ALS to [U.S. Secretary of War], 1849 Mar. 31; Gay, Horace and Cook, Ira (Box 3)
    A report of the arbitrators in the Ogden matter, describing the circumstances and data on which their appraisal of the Tonawanda improvements is based, together with a letter from the Department of the Interior, stating the document was accepted for the record only and is without an "official character."
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1849 Apr. 11; Angel, W. P. (Box 3)
    An acknowledgment of Ely's letter and its $10 enclosure.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1849 Apr. 30; Rice, A. G. (Box 3)
    A letter stating he is no longer interested in becoming Indian Agent at Ellicottville. Rice believes Osborn will be appointed to the post and that Shankland's hopes of being retained "will prove fallacious."
  - ALS to Peter Wilson, 1849 May 13; Parker, Nicholson H. (Box 3)
    Nic has received a letter from W. P. Angel, advising him to go to Lee and Co.'s bank in Buffalo to get money to bring the surviving Indians back from the West. He hesitates going without proof that the commission has been assigned to him officially.
  - ALS to W. P. Angel, 1849 May 14; Parker, Nicholson H. (Box 3)
    Nic acknowledges Angel's letter of May 12, advising him that money is on hand for his trip to the West to bring back surviving Cayugas. Nic requests instructions of an official character for identification purposes.
  - DS to William Parker, 1849 Aug. 15; Washington County Mutual Insurance Co. (Box 3)
    Policy covering five years fire insurance (1849-54), in the amount of $1,000, on house, farm buildings, personal effects, etc.
  - ALS to Nicholson H. Parker, 1849 Sept. 4; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 3)
    A letter offering to secure work for his brother at $1.25 a day on the canal between Canadea and Olean.
  - ALS to Caroline G. Parker, 1849 Nov. 13; Morgan, Lewis Henry, 1818-1881 (Box 3)
    Letter enclosing money in part payment of articles the Parker family are making and collecting for him. Morgan expects to visit Tonawanda at the end of the month.
  - ALS to Newton Parker, 1849 Dec. 19; Morgan, Lewis Henry, 1818-1881 (Box 3)
    Letter to Newton who has decided to return to school, encouraging and advising him in the matter of his studies. Morgan plans to send $2 each to Caroline and Nick in January in payment for moccasins and silverware, etc. He asks for Indian equivalents for a brief list of words.
  - Enlargement of the Erie Canal, [1849-1851?] (Box 3)
    Printed specification for excavations, locks, bridges, culverts, etc.
  - ALS to Caroline G. Parker, 1850 Jan. 20; [Porter, Charles Talbot] (Box 3)
    A letter signed `your brother Charles' acknowledging gifts of Indian bead and basket work.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1850 Mar. 14; King, John B. (Box 3)
    Letter telling Ely about a vacancy with the Engineer Corps at Lockport.
  - DS, 1850 Mar. 25; Tonawanda Chiefs (Box 3)
    Document, signed by 11 chiefs and 6 warriors, nullifying the sale of Lucy Parker's land by Lewis Poodry.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1850 Mar. 26; Seymour, S. (Box 3)
    Letter offering Ely a position as rodman on the Allegany River, under D.F. DeWitt at Little Valley.
  - ANS, 1850 Mar. 26; Tudale(?), B. G. (Box 3)
    Note stating that at the time of the surrender of its charter in 1848, Ely S. Parker was a member in good standing of Batavia Lodge No. 88.
  - ALS to [Ely S. Parker], 1850 May 29; Parker, Caroline (Box 3)
    A descriptive letter about her studies, teachers and classmates at the Albany State Normal School, which Caroline is attending with her brothers Newton and Nicholas.
  - ALS to Newton Parker, 1850 June 26; Parker, William and Elizabeth. (Box 3)
    A letter of parental advice to be a good boy and improve his mind.
  - ALS to [Jane?], 1850 July 17; Buckland, R. J. N. (Box 3)
    An incoherent letter, written to a sister apparently, concerning $20 which the writer wishes to borrow until he receives his salary as a teacher in the employ of Howard Nott in Union.
  - ALS to Caroline Parker, 1850 July 19; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 3)
    A letter to his sister at School, telling her to work hard and keep an eye on Newton. Ely has had favorable reports of her progress from Christopher Morgan.
  - ALS to Caroline [Parker], 1850 July 28; B., O. M. (Box 3)
    Letter from a boy friend in Pavilion Centre, which refers to their mutual friend Nett and a Ruth M. Bradly.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1850 Aug. 2; Morgan, Lewis Henry, 1818-1881 (Box 3)
    A letter thanking Ely for reporting the speeches "in such fine language," and requesting information on the relationship between Cornplanter and Handsome Lake.
  - ALS to Nicholson H. Parker, 1850 Aug. 28; Shanks, Isaac (Box 3)
    Letter stating he will send brooches and rattlesnakes as soon as possible.
  - ALS to Nicholson H. Parker, 1850 Sept. 1; Cone, Spencer H. (Box 3)
    Letter advising it seems a little too late to catch the rattlesnakes Nicholson has requested, and that the annual council will take place at Tonawanda on the 17th. This letter is signed `Gau-nos-qua.'
  - 1850 [Sept.] 26, [Wright, Asher?] (Box 3)
    Seneca text, without English, beginning "gan Dih ok nah 26 1850. Goh Da gas ga oh gr nok Dr yeh." 1-1/2 pages.
  - ALS to Caroline [Parker], 1850 Oct. 4; Smith, Lessie (Box 3)
    Letter from a former school mate with news of mutual friends.
  - "Book of Roots", 1850 Oct. 25; [Wright, Asher?] (Box 3)
    "Book of roots, or of words supposed to be roots... in the Seneca language." 4 pages in a small notebook inscribed at Allegany Mission.
  - ALS to Newton Parker, 1850 Nov. 4; Steele, J. F. (Box 3)
    A reply, addressed to Pembroke, acknowledging Newton's letter of October, and advising him that "his note to Miss Elizabeth" had been forwarded to New York.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1850 Dec. 16; Parker, Newton I. (Box 3)
    Newton would like to receive more mail from the family. Nick and he have lost their pocketbooks and some suspicion attaches to a student from Cattaraugus. Wishes to be addressed as Newton I. Parker, the I to stand for Isaac.
  - "The Indian Prophet", [1850?]; [Parker, Caroline G.] (Box 3)
    "The Indian Prophet," a corrected essay on Handsome Lake.
  - ALS to [J. H. Martindale], 1851 Feb. 8; [Parker, Ely S.] (Box 3)
    Incomplete draft of a letter to postpone a petition to the Legislature to appoint an attorney for the Tonawanda Indians.
  - ALS to Editor of the Albany Atlas, 1851 Mar. 1; Burroughs, Silas M. (Box 3)
    Concerning a plan for the speedy enlargement of the Erie Canal.
  - Act No. 374, 1851 Mar.7; New York State Assembly (Box 3)
    Reported by Mr. Varnum, in relation to measures for testing the title of land on the Tonawanda Indian Reservation. Two printed copies and original manuscript.
  - ALS to Nicholson H. Parker, 1851 Mar. 18; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 3)
    Ely thanks his brother for buying the shirts he ordered and sends him money, although he is as `poor as a church mouse' himself. He advises Nic to remain at school so as 'to get as good an education as it is possible for you to get.'
  - Bill No. 493, 1851 Mar. 20; New York State Assembly (Box 3)
    Reported by Mr. Burroughs, to authorize the laying out of a public highway on the bank of the Tonawanda and Oak Orchard canal feeder, with an amendment in manuscript to the effect that only Indians can settle on the said feeder.
  - Memorandum, 1851 Mar. [?]; Tonawanda Band of Seneca Indians (Box 3)
    Memorandum concerning money borrowed, to the amount of $433.25, for the purpose of sending a delegation to Albany.
  - ALS to A. H. H. Stuart, 1851 Apr. 3; Parker, Spencer Cone (Box 3)
    A letter to the Secretary of the Interior, protesting the removal of Dr. Peter Wilson as interpreter for the New York Agency.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1851 Apr. 5; Mau, Daniel (Box 3)
    A letter discussing copies of canal estimates.
  - ALS to [Ely S.?] Parker, 1851 Apr. 23; Washburne, C. T. (Box 3)
    A letter from the newly appointed Indian Agent stating he does `not feel free to interfere with what I believe to be the preference at Washington' to retain Dr. Peter Wilson as his interpreter.
  - ALS to Caroline Parker, 1851 May 14; [Parker, Spencer Cone] (Box 3)
    Brief letter advising that Jesse Tiffany and Ya-de-sose died Apr. 18 and Joh-doh on May 4. Charles Doctor and Eli Johnson are at school in Aurora. The letter is signed Gau-nos-qua.
  - ALS to Newton Parker, 1851 June 13; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 3)
    Letter of encouragement, expressing pleasure at his progress in school.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1851 June 19; Webster, Daniel (Box 3)
    A letter from Washington, thanking Ely for a gift copy of Morgan's "League of the Iroquois."
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1851 June 22; Parker, Nicholson H. (Box 3)
    Nick asks his brother for help in finding work during the summer vacation.
  - ALS to Nicholson H. Parker, 1851 June 24; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 3)
    Ely advises his brother that if the Bill for speedy enlargement of the Canal passes, he may be able to get him a job with the Engineers Dept.
  - "Wild roved an Indian girl, bright Alfarata", 1851 June?; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 3)
    Rough copy of what appears to be the words of a song. Verso of paper has notations concerning an increase in weight from Mar. to June 1851.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1851 July 13; Angel, W. P. (Box 3)
    A confidential letter informing Ely of a meeting with Mr. Fellows in Albany and of the latter's plan to "attempt to pay improvement money to the Tonawandas."
  - AL to Ely S. Parker, 1851 July 31; [Cone, Spencer H.] (Box 3)
    Letter advising that Nic's services as interpreter are needed at a trial in Batavia, and that in spite of some opposition on the part of Isaac Shanks and Jimmy Johnson that Parker will probably be made sachem. Letter signed Gaunosqua.
  - 1851 [July?], Buffalo Courier (Box 3)
    Account of a Council held for the purpose of celebrating the funeral rites of John Blacksmith, at which Ely S. Parker was proclaimed his successor as Grand Sachem of the Six Nations, and Spencer C. Parker and 8 others were installed as war chiefs.
  - Pr. LS, 1851 July; Morgan, Christopher (Box 3)
    A circular prepared by the Superintendent of Common Schools containing information to guide Town Superintendents in filling student vacancies at the State Normal School.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1851 [July?]; Pringle, Benjamin (Box 3)
    Second page only of a letter suggesting that Ely see Mr. Wadsworth.
  - ALS to Nicholson H. Parker, 1851 Aug. 22; Lansingh, K. V. R. (Box 3)
    Letter advising that the four shirts ordered have been sent by express to Rochester.
  - ALS to Spencer Cone Parker, 1851 Aug. 23; Brown, J. L. (Box 3)
    A vague letter to the effect the writer is willing to use his influence to bring about an arrangement to the advantage of the Indians, the Ogden Co. and the neighboring communities.
  - ALS to Spencer Cone Parker, 1851 Aug. 31; Rowe, Albert (Box 3)
    A confidential letter asking Spencer to use his influence on the writer's behalf in connection with the forthcoming state elections.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1851 Sept. 8; Colman, T. R. (Box 3)
    Letter requesting Ely to reserve a room at a reputable hotel for the use of the writer's brothers during the fair.
  - ALS to Nicholson Parker, 1851 Sept. 11; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 3)
    Brief letter concerning arrangements for forwarding Nic's luggage, share of annuities, etc.
  - ALS to Newton Parker, 1851 Sept. 15; Curtis, N. Baron (Box 3)
    Letter from a correspondent, now teaching school in Cynthiana, Ky., dealing with the marvels of modern travel, Cuban politics, etc.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1851 Sept. 19; Wilson, Peter (Box 3)
    A letter, in which reference is made to Ely's having been elected Sachem, asking him to have some baggage forwarded from Rochester to Buffalo.
  - ALS to Nicholson H. Parker, 1851 Sept. 22; Pierce, D. W. (Box 3)
    Letter from a friend attending school in Albany, describing vacation activities.
  - ALS to Nicholson H. Parker, 1851 Oct. 8; Pierce, Daniel W. (Box 3)
    Letter expressing hope that Nic will soon be well enough to return to school.
  - ALS to Spencer C. Parker, 1851 Oct. 8; Conrad, A. M. (Box 3)
    A letter from the Secretary of War, complying with a request to furnish a copy of President Fillmore's instructions to Benjamin Pringle, the agent appointed to disburse improvement monies to the Tonawandas. The copy of the instructions, enclosed with the Secretary's letter, is dated June 26, 1851.
  - DS to Ely S. Parker, 1851 Oct. 20; New York State Canal Board (Box 3)
    Certified extract from the Minutes of the Board, signed by F.H. Ruggles, relative to Ely's appointment as First Assistant Engineer on the Canals of the State.
  - ALS to Newton Parker, 1851 Nov. 4; Morgan, Lewis Henry, 1818-1881 (Box 3)
    Letter of encouragement and advice about school work.
  - ALS to Nicholson H. Parker, 1851 Nov. 6; Clarks, E. C. (Box 3)
    Brief letter from Engineer's Office at Lyons about payments to Nic in Oct. and Nov.
  - Diary, 1852 Jan. 1; Parker, Nicholson H. (Box 3)
    Torn page of a diary begun at the "house of W. W. Moore, corner of Spring and Hawk No. 37 in the city of Albany..."
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1852 Jan. 18; Hart, H. F. (Box 3)
    A confidential letter concerning purchasing a half interest in a Lock project with an Albert Hall.
  - ALS to J.B. Stittson, 1852 Jan. 23; McAlpin, William (Box 3)
    Instructions to a Division Engineer to furnish Mr. Conger, a member of the Senate Investigating Committee with copies of contracts and other information required by the Committee.
  - ALS to James White and John Burns, 1852 Feb. 17; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 3)
    Copy of lease to April 1854 of about 150 acres of land with house and barn on the Tonawanda Reservation.
  - ALS to William Parker, 1852 Feb. 20; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 3)
    Letter enclosing lease with White and Burns, asking his father to see that it is signed by them and its faithful performance guaranteed by a responsible party.
  - ALS to William Parker, 1852 Mar. 21; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 3)
    A letter to his father quoting an extract from the laws of 1841 (!) by which "it is proposed to commence the action against the settlers and other Whites upon the Tonawanda Reservation."
  - ADf, 1852 [Mar.?]; [Parker, Ely S.] (Box 3)
    Draft of a petition to invoke the Act of March 31, 1821 for removing White settlers on Indian lands by Aug. 20.
  - ALS to William Parker, 1852 Apr. 14; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 3)
    Letter advising that Ely and Martindale concur it would be unwise to start any more suits until the Blacksmith case and the case of removing settlers under the law of 1821 are settled.
  - ALS to [Seneca Indians], 1852 Apr. 19; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 3)
    A plea against the removal of Red Jacket's remains to Forest Lawn Cemetery.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1852 Apr. 29; Moore, F. H. (Box 3)
    Letter from a friend in the Treasury Dept., Washington, advising he will be glad to cooperate by sending Public Documents to Ely and Richard V. when requested to do so.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1852 May 4; Parker, Nicholson H. (Box 3)
    Letter stating he hopes to graduate next term and advising "we have been moving to 15 Lancaster," which prevented Nic's writing sooner.
  - ALS to William Parker, 1852 May 15; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 3)
    Letter expressing views on the leasing of water power, quarries, etc. to parties other than Indians.
  - ALS to Newton Parker, 1852 May 15; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 3)
    A letter referring to Ely's unsettled employment, plans for the summer, business interests at Tonawanda, and eagerness to learn the decision of the Court of Appeals. The letter is addressed to "Sir Isaac Newton Parker."
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1852 May 22; Cooper, George (Box 3)
    Letter from an uncle asking for instructions on the duties of his office as sub-sachem.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1852 May 27; Stockton, S. R. P. (Box 3)
    Letter from a friend, suggesting he attend a meeting at which Gov. Kossuth will speak and asking for an advance of $50.00.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1852 June 14; Moore, F. H. (Box 3)
    Letter advising that two of the three volumes requested have been sent by express and that the third volume will not be out until the next Congress. The books were apparently secured through the cooperation of [Daniel] Webster.
  - ALS to Ely Parker and J. H. Martindale, 1852 June 16; Parker, William and Parker, Samuel (Box 3)
    Letter suggesting that a delegation be sent to Washington to protest against the re-appointment of Benjamin Pringle.
  - ALS to Newton Parker, 1852 June 22; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 3)
    Letter replying that Ely `cannot dictate to George Cooper what he shall say or do in councils' and that he and Mr. Martindale concur that it would be `impolitic' to do anything about Pringle's agency before the Court of Appeals renders a decision. This letter also is addressed to "Sir Isaac Newton Parker."